A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, William J. Ronan, Series 29 FA371
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, William J. Ronan, Series 29
1947-1971, 1958-1971
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Morrow, Hugh
Boyd, Joseph H.
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Cannon, James M.
Whitman, Ann
Ronan, William J. (William John)
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
FA371
60 Document Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 29
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into the following 6 subseries:
Subseries 1 - Human Rights Issues Subseries 2 - Reference Files Subseries 3 - Arthur Levitt Clippings Subseries 4 - Legislation Subseries 5 - Speeches and Statements Subseries 6 - General Correspondence
Biographical/Historical note
William J. Ronan (b. November 8, 1912) served as Secretary to Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. He received his undergraduate degree magna cum laude at Syracuse University in 1934. He earned his Ph.D. in political science and economics at New York University. After graduating from NYU, Mr. Ronan taught there and served as administrative head of the Graduate Division of Public Service from 1939 to 1952. In 1953, he became Dean of the Graduate School of Public Administration and Social Service.
He served New York in several capacities prior to joining the Rockefeller administration. He was director of studies of the New York State Coordination Commission and conducted surveys of the State Education Department, the Civil Service Department, Public Authorities of New York State, the State Bureau of Motor Vehicles, and the nonjudicial positions in the state courts.
He became closely affiliated with Governor Rockefeller beginning in 1956, when Ronan served as the Executive Director of the Temporary State Commission on the Constitutional Convention and also of its successor organization, the Special Legislative Committee on Revision and Simplification of the Constitution. Ronan later became First Deputy City Administrator of the City of New York and served at the federal level with the Department of State and the Civil Service Commission. During his last two years as Governor Rockefeller's Secretary, Ronan also headed the Metropolitan Transit Authority.
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains office files of William J. Ronan. They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series primarily covers the years when William Ronan served Nelson Rockefeller as Secretary to the Governor, 1959 to 1966. From 1965 to 1966, Ronan also served as head of the Metropolitan Transit Authority. The bulk of this series is composed of reports prepared for Governor Rockefeller by various state departments and agencies. Some of these reports duplicate those found in Record Group 15, Series 28, Departmental Reports.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Civil service; Civil service -- New York (State); Economics; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public policy; Public relations; State governments -- United States; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Civil defense; Civil defense -- United States; Arms control; Arms control -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); International economic relations; Human rights; International relations -- United States; International relations; Legislation -- New York (State); Latin America; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- Human Rights Issues, 1959-1964; 1; 1.6 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries is devoted to the issues of Human and Civil Rights. It covers all aspects from housing and unemployment discrimination to education and religion. An entire state agency focused on human rights, known as the State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD) and later the State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR). This series is composed primarily of clippings, memoranda, and correspondence on various human rights topics that arose in the state.
  - Censorship and Obscenity in Mass Media (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1959 report of the New York State Joint Legislative Committee Studying the Publication and Dissemination of Offensive and Obscene Material; clippings on censorship; correspondence on censorship issues.
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from the State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD); statements, speeches and remarks issued by SCAD; correspondence, memoranda, press releases from the State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR).
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Employment (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from the State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD) and State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR); clippings on [un]employment issues.
  - Employment (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ethics Charges, Gambling, Divorce (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Clippings.
  - Housing, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD); clippings on Housing discrimination.
  - Housing, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Housing, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD) and State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR); remarks by NAR on Housing issues.
  - Housing, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Housing, Paul Zuber Charges, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Information on lawsuit brought against the State Commission Against Discrimination on behalf of an African-American who was denied housing in a complex in Westchester County.
  - John Birch Society and Right Wing (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Clippings on John Birch Society activities in the United States.
  - Public Accommodations and Voting (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD) and State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR); report on the Federal Voting Assistance Program.
  - Religion (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases from the State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD) and the State Commission for Human Rights (SCHR); clippings on religious issues, including birth control, school prayer, and loyalty oaths.
  - Religion (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Schools - City College Case, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Information on alleged bias against Hispanics at the City College of New York (CCNY), report submitted by president of college.
  - Schools - College and Academic Freedom (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Clippings on students exercising their First Amendment rights at college campuses nationwide.
  - Schools - Communism (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Curriculum reports, clippings, position papers on "Teaching About Communism in New York Schools."
  - Schools - New Rochelle School Integration Case, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Clippings on legal fight to desegregate the Lincoln School, a primarily black school in Westchester County.
  - Schools - New York State School Integration (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Clippings, reports, memoranda on efforts to achieve balance in New York State schools.
  - Schools - Queens College Case, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Legal materials, clippings, memoranda on case involving religious discrimination at Queens College, brought by faculty of college, involving the State Commission Against Discrimination (SCAD).
  - Schools - Queens College Case, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Schools (Box 3, Folder 25)
    General information, correspondence, memoranda on discrimination issues in school nationwide.
  - Schools (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Clippings on discrimination issues in schools nationwide.
  - State Commission for Human Rights (Formerly SCAD) (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and press releases on the government agency tasked to resolve civil and human rights issues in New York State.
  - State Commission for Human Rights (Formerly SCAD) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Strikes and Allied Union Activities (Including Schools) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Clippings and memoranda on strikes in New York State, including unlawful actions taken by school unions.
- Reference Files, 1945-1971; 2; 17.4 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  This subseries is arranged alphabetically by department or agency.
  This subseries consists primarily of the annual reports of individual state departments or agencies. While the Rockefeller administration did not begin until January 1, 1959, Ronan was sent annual reports of agencies for several years prior to its beginning. The subseries primarily covers the years 1959 through 1962. The final ten boxes of this subseries are an amalgam of publications covering a wide range of issues. The last box (box 47) contains primarily bound volumes of published reports.
  - Agriculture - 1959 Annual Report of the Department of Agriculture & Markets, Don J. Wickham, Commissioner (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Agriculture - 1960 Annual Report of the Department of Agriculture & Markets, Don J. Wickham, Commissioner (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Agriculture - 1961 Annual Report of the Department of Agriculture & Markets, Don J. Wickham, Commissioner (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Alcohol - 1958 Annual Report of the Activities of the State Liquor Authority, Division of Alcoholic Beverage Control (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Alcohol - 1959 Annual Report of the Activities of the State Liquor Authority, Division of Alcoholic Beverage Control (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Alcohol - 1960 Annual Report of the Activities of the State Liquor Authority, Division of Alcoholic Beverage Control (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Alcohol - 1961 Annual Report of the Activities of the State Liquor Authority, Division of Alcoholic Beverage Control (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Comptroller - 1954 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, J. Raymond McGovern (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Comptroller - 1955 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Comptroller - 1956 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Comptroller - 1957 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Comptroller - 1958 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Comptroller - 1959 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Comptroller - Fiscal and Population Data for Units of Local Government in Metropolitan and Non-Metropolitan Counties, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Comptroller - 1960 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Comptroller - Financial Data for School Districts, Year Ending June 30, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Comptroller - State Aid to Local Government, A Brief Description of the Current Types of Financial Assistance Showing Purpose, Methods of Apportionment, Statutory Citations and Trends in Amounts Distributed, September 1961 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Comptroller - 1961 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Comptroller - 1962 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Comptroller - Financial Data for School Districts, Year Ending June 30, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Comptroller - 1963 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Comptroller - Digest of 1963 Annual Report of the Comptroller of the State of New York, Arthur Levitt (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Comptroller - Financial Data for School Districts, Year Ending June 30, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Superintendent of Banks - An Analysis of the Licensed Lender Industry, New York State, 1945-1957 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Superintendent of Banks - One Hundred Fourth Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1954, William A. Lyon, Superintendent of Banks (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Superintendent of Banks - One Hundred Fifth Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1955, George A. Mooney, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Superintendent of Banks - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1958, George A. Mooney, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Superintendent of Banks - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1960, G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Rate Regulation and the Struggle for Savings", March 7, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Annual Conference of Savings and Mortgage Division, American Bankers Association, Roosevelt Hotel, New York City.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Interest Rates: Their Impact on Commercial Banking", March 16, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the American Institute of Banking, Boston Chapter, Federal Reserve Bank of Boston, Boston.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Savings Competition and Bank Regulation in the United States", June 14, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Sixth International Savings Bank Congress, Stockholm, Sweden.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "The Banking Department's Role in the Legislative Process", October 14, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Banking Law Section of the New York Bar Association, Syracuse, New York.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "The New York Pattern for Banking in the Sixties", October 25, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Iowa Bankers Association, 74th Annual Convention, Des Moines, Iowa.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Savings Bank Liquidity", November 9, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Annual Convention, Savings Banks Association of New York State, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia.
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Puerto Rican Banking: Challenges and Opportunities", November 29, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the Puerto Rico Bankers Association, San Juan, Puerto Rico.
  - Superintendent of Banks - The New York State Banking Department, Legislative Summary, 1960, G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Some Observations on Common Banking Problems", March 5, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the American Institute of Banking.
  - Superintendent of Banks - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1961, Oren Root, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Superintendent of Banks - "The Responsibilities and Obligations of Savings Banks", February 24, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Remarks of William S. Brennen, First Deputy Superintendent of Banks before the Mortgage and Finance Conference Group V, Savings Bank Association of the State of New York, Brooklyn, New York.
  - Superintendent of Banks - List of Securities Considered Legal Investments for New York Savings Banks, July 1, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Superintendent of Banks - "Desirable Legal Changes for Creating a Better National Mortgage Market", May 2, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    Remarks of G. Russell Clark, Superintendent of Banks before the First National Mortgage Conference, American Bankers Association, Washington, D.C.
  - Superintendent of Banks - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1962, Oren Root, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Superintendent of Banks - Annual Report of the Superintendent of Banks, State of New York, 1963, Oren Root, Superintendent of Banks (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Superintendent of Banks - Branch Banking, Bank Mergers, and the Public Interest - A Summary Report, January 1964 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Civil Service - Classification and Compensation Plan and Salary Schedules, Civil Service Department, September 1, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Civil Service - Seventy-seventh Annual Report, New York State Department of Civil Service and Civil Service Commission, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Civil Service - Annual Salary Study, 1959, Department of Civil Service, Division of Classification and Compensation (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Civil Service - Annual Report, New York State Department of Civil Service and Civil Service Commission, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Civil Service - Annual Salary Study, 1960, Department of Civil Service, Division of Classification and Compensation (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Civil Service - Seventy-ninth Annual Report, New York State Department of Civil Service and Civil Service Commission, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Civil Service - Annual Salary Study, 1961, Department of Civil Service, Division of Classification and Compensation (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Civil Service - Eightieth Annual Report, New York State Department of Civil Service and Civil Service Commission, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Civil Service - Annual Report, New York State Department of Civil Service and Civil Service Commission, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Department of Commerce - 100 Services of the New York State Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Department of Commerce - "This is New York State" (Box 8, Folder 84)
    Historical brochure about New York State, published by the Department of Commerce.
  - Department of Commerce - Personal Income in Counties of New York State, 1948-1957, Supplement to December 1958 issue of New York State Commerce Review (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Department of Commerce - 1958 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Edward T. Dickinson, Commissioner (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Department of Commerce - 1959 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Department of Commerce - Local Planning and Zoning, 1959 Edition (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Department of Commerce - Personal Income in Counties of New York State, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Department of Commerce - Zoning in New York State, A Guide to the Preparation of Zoning Ordinances, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Department of Commerce - 1960 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Department of Commerce - Directory of Industrial Research Laboratories in New York State, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Department of Commerce - Local Planning and Zoning, 1960 Edition (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Department of Commerce - New York State and Local Tax Structure, Part I - State Taxes, June 1, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Department of Commerce - Personal Income in Counties in New York State, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Department of Commerce - Taxes and Plant Location in New York and Other Industrial States, October 1960 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Department of Commerce - 1961 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Department of Commerce - Control of Land Subdivision, A Manual of Subdivision Regulations for Municipal Officials, Subdivision Developers, Builders and Planning Boards, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Department of Commerce - Local Planning and Zoning, 1961 Edition (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Department of Commerce - Zoning in New York State, A Guide to the Preparation of Zoning Ordinances, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Department of Commerce - 1962 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Department of Commerce - Zoning in New York State, A Guide to the Preparation of Zoning Ordinances, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Department of Commerce - 1963 Annual Report, Department of Commerce, Keith S. McHugh, Commissioner (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Department of Commerce - Local Planning and Zoning, 1963 Edition (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Conservation Department - Forty-eighth Annual Report, 1958, Conservation Department, Sharon J. Mauhs, Commissioner (Box 9, Folder 105)